<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sixth part of The Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator being a just defence against the reproach of scandalous tongues and pens : and a proper looking-glass for a meeting in London, termed the second-days meeting, who are reputed the approvers of three books, or papers against a treatise entituled, The Christian-quaker, &amp;c. in five parts given forth by W.R. on behalf of himself and other friends in truth concerned / by W.R.</title>
            <title>Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator. Part 6</title>
            <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R970</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13658066</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13658066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1045:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sixth part of The Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator being a just defence against the reproach of scandalous tongues and pens : and a proper looking-glass for a meeting in London, termed the second-days meeting, who are reputed the approvers of three books, or papers against a treatise entituled, The Christian-quaker, &amp;c. in five parts given forth by W.R. on behalf of himself and other friends in truth concerned / by W.R.</title>
                  <title>Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator. Part 6</title>
                  <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.R. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: William Rogers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101053:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101053:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SIXTH PART OF THE Chriſtian-Quaker, Diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Apoſtate &amp; Innovator,</hi> BEING <hi>A J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST DEFENCE</hi> Againſt the Reproach of Scandalous <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>Pens,</hi> AND A <hi>PROPER LOOKING-GLASS</hi> for a Meeting in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> termed <hi>The Second-days Meeting,</hi> who are reputed the Approvers of three Books, or Papers againſt a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> Entituled, <hi>The Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> &amp;c. in Five Parts given forth by <hi>W. R.</hi> on behalf of himſelf and other Friends in Truth concerned.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.13.</hi>
               </bibl> But Evil Men and Seducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and being deceived.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. R.</hi> In the Year, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101053:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101053:2"/>
            <head>The SIXTH PART OF THE <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> Diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Apoſtate and Innovator,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <p>DID my own Reputation as a Man, or Chriſtian, lie on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at Stake, I might the ſooner ſatisfie my ſelf to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in ſilence, patiently to undergo the unjuſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of ſcandalous <hi>Tongues</hi> and <hi>Pens;</hi> and ſolace my ſelf with the Enjoyment of that <hi>Inward Peace,</hi> which the Lord through his Mercy hath (in the midſt of all my Exerciſes, for the clearing of my Conſcience) made me Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of.</p>
               <p>But, when I conſider what Multitudes of the weaker ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are apt to be deceived, by imbracing <hi>Shadows</hi> inſtead of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> and <hi>Lies</hi> for <hi>Truth,</hi> taking their meaſures of ſome Friends more from the reproachful and ſcandalous Terms, undeſervedly given by our <hi>Oppoſers,</hi> than from Matter of Fact committed, or any real ground of Conviction, that ſuch have merited our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminating
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101053:3"/>Reflections, it hath been one Motive amongſt others, occaſioning me once more to appear in Print: and one part of my end therein is, that ſome ſhort diſcovery (in a few Lines) may be made (ſo far as at preſent I find freedom in the <hi>Truth</hi>) of the ways and meanes by which ſome ſimple-minded Friends have been betrayed to reproach their Friends and Neighbours, when in reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they have had no juſt cauſe ſo to do, unleſs a declared Diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction touching <hi>George Fox,</hi> or others of Party with him, on juſt occaſion, ſhall, without any manner of Examination, be deemed ſuch.</p>
               <p>In order to what I have premiſed, I ſhall take a little notice of three Printed Books, or Papers againſt the Book Entituled, <hi>The Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt,</hi> In the Name of <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor,</hi> contains two Sheets three Quarters, and is Printed for <hi>John Bringhurſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second,</hi> In the Name of <hi>Thomas Laurence,</hi> containeth a part of a Sheet, and the price thereof (as he tells his Roader) is an half-penny, Printed for <hi>Benjamin Clark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Third,</hi> Is partly in the Name of <hi>John Pennington,</hi> and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Name of his Mother <hi>Mary Pennington,</hi> and contains two Sheets, Printed alſo for <hi>Benjamin Clark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I take notice of any thing therein contained, I think meet to inform the Reader, that the ſcope of their writing,
<note n="*" place="margin">Note, <hi>A Reply to the ſaid Book, is ready for the Preſs.</hi>
                  </note> and Names of Perſons for whom they are Printed, compared to what I find written in the 12th. Page of the <hi>Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> of a Book againſt the <hi>Chriſtian-Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> in the Name of the <hi>Second-days Meeting,</hi> are ſufficient Evidence to Intelligent Perſons among the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> that they are given forth by the Approbation of a <hi>Meeting</hi> uſually conſiſting of uncertain numbers of uncertain qualified Perſons, called the <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> in <hi>London;</hi> who though they may pretend themſelves to be inveſted with <hi>Spiritual Power</hi> to correct or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs what is brought before them; yet let all Friends know that theſe few Lines will remain as a Record to the <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> of ſuch as have approved ſuch undeſerved unchriſtian-like Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and Treatment, wherewith the aforeſaid Books or Papers are ſtuft, as by theſe few Lines is made appear.</p>
               <p>The Conſideration hereof occaſions me to ſignifie that one part of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101053:3"/>my Concern to take notice of the aforeſaid Books or Papers, is more to diſcover what is acted under Pretence of that <hi>Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> whereof the ſaid <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> is a part, than to detect the Perſons whoſe Names are ſubſcribed to them, and ſo leave every Readers Judgment free, how far this Diſcovery ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them guilty of abominable Wickedneſs and Deceit.</p>
               <p>'Tis frequently brought to my Ears, that our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> common Diſcourſe is, <q>That I have written a wicked Book againſt the Faithful Friends of Truth, that if all I had therein written were true, yet the Spirit that gave it forth, muſt be wrong, and the ſame with <hi>Hams,</hi> becauſe it diſcovers the Nakedneſs of a Father, and publiſheth it in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon,</hi> to make the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed</hi> rejoyce:</q> and ſuch as diſlike it on this ground, have deſired that it might be called in again.</p>
               <p>This Diſcourſe I am willing firſt to take notice of, becauſe by the ſcope of the aforeſaid Books, it ſeems to be the ſenſe of the Givers forth, and Apprevors there of.</p>
               <p>If the meer diſcovering of Nakedneſs by one
<note n="*" place="margin">Note, John Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington <hi>in the firſt page of his Complaint, acknowledgeth me a Profeſſor of Truth.</hi>
                  </note> Profeſſor of Truth againſt another be a Sin, then doubtleſe Paul was ſuch a ſort of Sinner in leaving it on Record, <hi>That he withſtood</hi> Peter (the Eldeſt Apoſtle) <hi>to the face, becauſe he was to be blamed for his Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation:</hi> [Read the 2d. Chapter to the <hi>Galatians</hi>] and if any ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> publiſhed it not in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askelon,</hi> To this I anſwer, that from the 14th. verſe of the ſaid Chapter, we learn, that <hi>Pauls</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof was before all men, his words are theſe, <hi>But when I ſaw that they went not the right way to the Truth of the Goſpel, I ſaid unto</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>before all men, If thou being a</hi> Jew, <hi>liveſt as the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and not like the</hi> Jews, <hi>why conſtraineſt thou the</hi> Gentiles <hi>to do like the</hi> Jews. I ſhall now leave it to the conſideration of ſuch as are acquainted with <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Actions, whether <hi>Peters</hi> Diſſimulation be not a proper <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> for <hi>George</hi> to behold his Face in, witneſs his Advice to <hi>Mary Pennington</hi> to ſecure Worldly-Eſtate from the Spoiler, when 'twas likely to be ſeized for Obedience to Chriſts Command, compared with his reflecting Paper, touching making away Eſtates from the Spoiler in time of Perſecution for Worſhip of God, according to the Apoſtle's Counſel: witneſs his advice to <hi>Nathanael Crips</hi> and <hi>Robert Arch</hi> to buy their Tithes, compared with his known Severity at other times againſt Payment of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101053:4"/>Tyths. Witneſs his Advice to Friends in general, not to Judge one another, nor to lay open one anothers Weakneſs behind one anothers back, nor yet to Back-bite, and yet behaves himſelf in his Travel, as if 'twas great part, if not the chief part of his Buſineſs ſo to do. Witneſs his Counſel to follow Reports until the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reporter was found, and yet take liberty to hear and receive Backbiting Reports againſt his Friends, and not only ſo, but to hide the Reporter when the Matter hath been denied, that this hath been his State, I am capable for to prove, ſee <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> 5th. <hi>Part, Pages</hi> 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 24, 25, 54, 55, 8.</p>
               <p>'Tis alſo obſervable, (as appears in divers Parts of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Quaker</hi>) That <hi>George Fox,</hi> and divers others of Party with him have endeavoured to diſcover Nakedneſs in their Brethren, which being to my knowledge very publickly known amongſt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> I think it the leſs needful to cite Inſtances hereof: And though 'twas from a wrong Spirit in <hi>Ham</hi> to uncover his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Nakedneſs, yet it is a falſe Application to me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> concerned in the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker.</hi> For
<note n="*" place="margin">Note, <hi>See Chriſtian-Quaker</hi> 5th. <hi>Part, Pages</hi> 85, 86, 87, 88. <hi>and the Preface. Many other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances might be cited.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>George Fox</hi>'s endeavouring to uncover pretended Nakedneſs in his Brother, or Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſending abroad Certificates thereof to be ſpread amongſt Enemies as well as Friends, was one occaſion that we did proceed to proſs, thereby to act the part (not of Curſed <hi>Ham</hi>) but of that Man of God who committed <hi>Ham</hi>'s Action (even as we have done the like of <hi>George Fox</hi>'s) to Poſterity.</p>
               <p>Object. Some may ſay, <hi>That neither</hi> George Fox, <hi>nor his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have publiſhed the Nakedneſs of any Brethren amongſt ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> profeſſed not the Truth. But if Report be true, thine hath been publiſh't amongſt Prieſts and others, not reputed Friends, or ſo much as owning the Principle of Truth in which we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If any ſhall ſo object, I may reaſonably ſuppoſe that they are ſuch as have ſuckt in ſuch Advice as <hi>John Bringhurſt</hi> gives in his Preface to <hi>Chriſtopher Taylors</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>Not to read
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101053:4"/>The Book Entituled the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> and not only ſo, but may be at Unity with a new ſort of Doctrine publiſhed in ſome publick Meetings for Worſhip of God, to this effect, that as in the natural Body, the <hi>Eye</hi> is placed to ſee for the reſt of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſo in the Spiritual Body, God hath placed one Member as an <hi>Eye,</hi> to ſee for the reſt:</q> And on the Foot of this Doctrine, and the aforeſaid Advice, approved by ſome termed Brethren, (unto whom alſo we have been exhorted to have an Eye) may not da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to read the ſaid Book, which if they had, they might in the 11th. page of the Preface, have been informed that <hi>George Fox</hi> ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad three Certificates touching <hi>John Story,</hi> with direction to ſhew them both to Enemies and Friends, which doubtleſs were in order to diſcover ſome pretended Nakedneſs in him, and that <hi>Joan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (whom I may term <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Factor in <hi>Briſtol</hi> (if it be proper to ſpeak in his own Language) ſhewed a Letter written by <hi>Glorge Fox</hi> to defame me undeſervedly unto one <hi>Jeſeph Forreſt,</hi> Who was never accounted as I know, or ever heard to be of the People called <hi>Quaker</hi>) as in the 18th. page of the the 5th. <hi>Part</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker</hi> doth appear. <hi>Moreover</hi> in the 28, 29, 30 Pages of the <hi>Poſt-ſcript</hi> to the Preface of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> are cited divers Paſſages out of ſome Printed Papers publiſhed in the Name of <hi>Ann Whitehead</hi> and <hi>Mary Elſon,</hi> which import a Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Diviſion in Print particularly relating (as <hi>Mary Elſon</hi>'s words are) to her Native Country <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> and this before the Publication of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> for it was not then wholly Printed, if it had, it could not have contained any Citation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I alſo well remember (being an Ear-witneſs) that <hi>Robert Langley</hi> of <hi>Naylſworth</hi> vilified and deſamed <hi>John Story</hi> by Name, end that in the preſence of <hi>George Fox,</hi> on the <hi>Firſt-day</hi> of the week, in a publick Meeting for Worſhip of God, within the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> ſome years paſt, before (as we ſuppoſed) 1500 People, of whom many were no Profeſſors of Truth (it being then the time of a Fair) and yet no Reproof from <hi>George Fox,</hi> or any of his Party was then manifeſted, nor yet at any time after, ſo far as ever I did hear; 'tis to be doubted that he well approved that Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for I could, and doubt not, but yet can bring Teſtimony, that <hi>George Fox</hi> ſuddenly after his Departure out of the ſaid Meeting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to a Friend of <hi>John Stories,</hi> to this effect: <hi>If</hi> John Story <hi>be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101053:5"/>your Chriſt, then take him:</hi> 'twas an unſavoury Expreſſion in him in many reſpects, and ſeems to import that at that time, ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man, viſible to <hi>Carnal Eyes</hi> (as <hi>John Story</hi> was) was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at that day to be Chriſt; thoſe who are Friends to <hi>John Story,</hi> as well as to the Truth, deteſt the thoughts of owning any mortal Man <hi>to be the Chriſt of God:</hi> and ſince the weakneſs of <hi>Solomon Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> (to go at preſent no farther) hath given very publick occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of diſcourſe touching <hi>George Fox,</hi> as if he were the — it is become Cauſe of Admiration to ſome, that <hi>George Fox</hi> hath not more publickly than is yet known, and that by Print too, declared himſelf to be a mortal Man: his Pen would have been far better exerciſed in ſuch a work, than it was in giving ſuch an idle flout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ſcornful Anſwer to <hi>John Wilkingſon</hi> as he did on the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſaying that <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Body muſt turn to duſt, ſee the 4th. Part of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> pag. 48, 68, 69, 70.</p>
               <p>As to the Publication of my Book, as in the <hi>Objection,</hi> I have this to ſay; though 'twas never my practiſe, order, or advice to publiſh it amongſt <hi>Prieſts:</hi> yet 'tis impoſſible for me to prove that it hath not a Such ſort of Negatives under my Circumſtances cannot be proved. However I muſt acknowledge it hath been at ſome time under my Conſideration, that conſidering the Caſe in all its Circumſtances, it would have been no Breach of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty if I had proclaimed it even in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon,</hi> becauſe I did diſcharge my Duty towards ſuch as once I accounted my Brethren, as may be ſeen at large in my Book, and in particular, in the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> and <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> thereto. And on the whole Matter, it appears to me that they are ſo far from acknowledging their Errour, as that they perſiſt therein like Perſons hating to be reformed; and not only ſo, but I have been evily intreated for ſo doing, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours have been uſed to ſhut the Door amongſt <hi>Profeſſed Friends</hi> againſt me, ſo as that my juſt Complaint ſhould not be heard. And in as much as <hi>Briſtol</hi> was threatned to be an <hi>Anvil</hi> to beat upon, and ſince hath been ſo made, and my ſelf by Name in a publick <hi>Meeting</hi> reflected on, even in the ſame Language as <hi>Eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as</hi> the <hi>Sorcerer</hi> was, and by that meanes become the Subject of divers ſort of Peoples Diſcourſe, both of <hi>Profeſſor</hi> and <hi>Prophane,</hi> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Coffee-Houſes,</hi> and other publick Places, I thought it but juſt that ſome particular Friends that were ſober Perſons, and with whom I had dealing ſhould have the ſight of my <hi>Defence,</hi> and on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101053:5"/>that Foot I aſſented that two or three Perſons might have the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to have them, if they would, but when I underſtood that that very Aſſent might become an Offence to ſome, I for their Sakes, more than any other Obligation on my ſelf, as a Chriſtian, did give order (which I can prove by many Witneſſes) that none ſhould be diſpoſed or lent to any that Profeſſed not the Truth, and to this day, I have not, neither is it in my Thoughts at preſent (without ſome further Motive) to contradict it, notwithſtanding I have been reflected upon as a Perſon hiding my <hi>Talent</hi> in the Earth, becauſe I would not aſſent to the ſight thereof, when deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Let the ingenious Reader now conſider, whether what I have done amounts to a Publication thereof in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I now come to ſhew that if I had publiſh't the ſaid Book amongſt the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed</hi> in a general way, yet the alluſion to what was forbidden to be publiſh't in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon,</hi> is very improper in my Caſe.</p>
               <p>From the <hi>Scripture of Truth</hi> we learn (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.20.) that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Counſel was, <hi>That the Death of</hi> Saul <hi>ſhould not be publiſhed in</hi> Gath, <hi>nor in the Streets of</hi> Askalon, <hi>leſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce:</hi> but yet we alſo learn (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.18, 19. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.8. compared with 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.24, 25.) that though <hi>Sauls</hi> Kingdom was rent from him, and he ſlain, becauſe of his Rebellion, yet he acknowledged his Sin, and prayed that his Sin might be taken away: but as for <hi>George Fox</hi> (touching whom a <hi>Concern of Conſcience</hi> for Truths Sake, was with me to treat as I have done) I underſtand not that he is in any wiſe come to an acknowledgment of his Sin, as <hi>Saul</hi> was, much leſs to pray that it might be taken away. Oh that the day were come wherein he might have a real Senſe thereof: and if it were ſo, that the Lord ſuffered <hi>Saul</hi> for his Rebellion, to fall on the <hi>High Places,</hi> notwithſtanding he hearkened to the <hi>Word of the Lord,</hi> through the Mouth of his Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſo as to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his Sin, and pray that it might be taken from him; me-thinks it ſhould be a warning to <hi>George Fox</hi> and others of his Party, to hearken unto the <hi>Word of the Lord</hi> that came unto his Servant <hi>John Wilkingſon,</hi> the 20th. day of the 6th. month 1675, which was on this wiſe, <hi>viz. To repent and turn from their Proceedings, and leave Gods People to the Order of his Goſpel and Command, and that if they would not, then the Lord himſelf would break them, and turn them one againſt another about their Orders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am well ſenſible to what a height of Confidence our <hi>Oppoſers</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101053:6"/>are aſcended, and do heartily breath unto the God of Heaven, that they may be humbled before the Lord; and in particular, for that high and lofty one <hi>George Fox,</hi> that ſo he may not utterly fall in the height of his vain Imagination, even as <hi>Saul</hi> did on the <hi>High Places</hi> for his Rebellion.</p>
               <p>Tis next with me to treat a little on the advice of ſome to call in my Book, which occaſions me in the firſt place thus to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
               <p>There are <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Seaſons</hi> wherein (in a more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſerious manner) my heart is even ript open, naked and bare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and in a ſenſe of his Love in calling me (amongſt many others) to the acknowledgment of the <hi>Truth,</hi> hath it pleaſed the Lord to tender me, and in that <hi>Frame of Spirit</hi> I have moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly examined my ſelf, with reſpect to the <hi>Work</hi> I have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in, and called unto, and for which I now ſuffer Reproach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſervedly: and this I in the <hi>Truth</hi> can ſay, that of all the Actions of my Life, ſince the day of my Remembrance, I know not of one in which I have more Peace, and Content, and Satisfaction than in the preparing, printing, and publiſhing, ſo far as I yet have, the Book Entituled, <hi>The Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> and therefore I dare not call it in on the Foot of ſuch Advice, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>I remember the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> Counſel to the <hi>Romans</hi> of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Perſwaſions in ſome things was, <hi>To follow after the things which make for Peace.</hi> This Counſel hath been very effectually followed on our Part, Witneſs a Letter written by <hi>John Story</hi> to two Meetings in the <hi>North,</hi> viz. That called Quarterly, and that called Separate, a Letter written by <hi>William Ford</hi> and my ſelf, and another by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Eaſtmead</hi> and <hi>John Mattraverſe</hi> at <hi>Briſtol-Fair,</hi> when <hi>George Fox,</hi> &amp; many others at Unity with them were there. The <hi>Teſtimony</hi> given by my ſelf at the Houſe of <hi>Simon Clements,</hi> before eighty Perſons at a Meeting occaſioned by reaſon of Differences: the Import of ſome part of all being to manifeſt, that on our Part, we were deſirous that all Offences might be forgiven &amp; forgotten, and that Friends might embrace each other in that antient Love which was witneſſed in the Beginning, being no way deſirous to exalt our ſelves above our Brethren, or to condeſcend to no other Terms of Peace, than ſuch as ſhould tend to the Exaltation of one Party above another.</p>
               <p>Moreover when I was laſt in <hi>London,</hi> I made a Propoſition to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Friends in words to this Effect, that I was ready to aſſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Meeting of both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arties, for two limited ends.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101053:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To Invocate the Name of the Lord for forgiveneſs of all Offences and Treſpaſſes committed againſt him on either ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As we might expect an <hi>Anſwer</hi> from God, ſo to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to forgive each other all manner of Treſpaſſes reſpectively ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended to have been committed each againſt other.</p>
               <p>Who can deny, but that the firſt propoſed <hi>End</hi> is a <hi>Chriſtian-Propoſition</hi> on our Part: perhaps ſome proud <hi>Phariſee</hi> may, I mean, ſuch as may be apt to ſay, <hi>Stand off, I am more Holy than thou.</hi> If the <hi>firſt</hi> be a <hi>Chriſtian-Propoſition,</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> cannot be leſs, except it may truly be termed <hi>Chriſtian Fruit</hi> to expect Forgiveneſs of God, and not be ready to forgive one another.</p>
               <p>Object. If any object, <hi>We are ready to forgive Perſonal Treſpaſſes, but yet that will not tend to make a perfect Peace between us, becauſe you are not in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with the Brethren touching neceſſary things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the</hi> Church <hi>ſince</hi> Church-Government <hi>hath been eſtabliſh't amongſt us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Note, <hi>I uſe the word</hi> Eſtabliſht <hi>for that I find the Word</hi> Eſtabliſh't <hi>uſed to that purpoſe in the Writings of our Oppoſers.</hi>
                  </note> This <hi>Objection</hi> hints not at any Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences touching Principles and Doctrines held forth amongſt us before <hi>Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was pretended to be Eſtabliſh't, and may very properly be compared to the Difference ſignified of by <hi>Paul</hi> amongſt the <hi>Believing-Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> If our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> believe the Apoſtle, as we do, they will then find in the 14th. Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> that he deſcribes two ſorts of <hi>Believers,</hi> but doth not ſignifie, that for their <hi>Differing Perſwaſions</hi> they were out of Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Body; but rather the contrary is imported by his <hi>Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own Mind, Let us not therefore Judge one another any more.</hi> Verſe 2d. of the ſaid Chapter-<hi>Pauls</hi> very Words run thus, <hi>One believeth that he may eat of all Things, and another which is weak, eateth Herbs.</hi> The ſcope of that Chapter clearly ſhews, that he which limited himſelf to the eating <hi>Herbs,</hi> was but the weak Brother, and that the Brother differing from him, was the ſtronger, as by theſe words are ſignified, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>I know, and am perſwaded through the Lord Jeſus, that there is nothing unclean of it ſelf.</hi> By this (it ſeems to me) that ſuch as limit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to one Outward Method touching proceeding in a Marriage, or relieving the Poor, are but the weaker Brethren, and therefore very unfit to pretend themſelves <hi>Church-Governours,</hi> or to quote any of <hi>Pauls</hi> Words, as an Argument to inveſt themſelves in ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101053:7"/>an Office; but yet may be apt to tell us, as in the <hi>Objection, We can have no perfect Peace with ſuch as are out of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The word <hi>Peace,</hi> uſed as aforeſaid, occaſions me to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a Senſe be not expreſly contrary to <hi>Pauls</hi> Teſtimony and Counſel on the occaſion of two ſorts of <hi>Believers,</hi> as aforeſaid. <hi>Pauls</hi> words are theſe, <hi>The Kingdom of God is not Meat nor Drink, but Righteouſneſs and Peace, and Joy in the Holy-Ghoſt.</hi> Let us then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low theſe things which make for Peace; this clearly ſhews that ſuch as had, or ſhould Judge each other about <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks,</hi> (which were <hi>Outward Things</hi>) were ſuch as did not follow Peace, and not only ſo, but that Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Ghoſt might be witneſſed by ſuch as were of different Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touching theſe <hi>Outward Things.</hi> And if <hi>George Fox</hi> did in years that are paſt, write as he meant, 'twas then far from his thoughts to ſet up <hi>Outward Things,</hi> much leſs endeavour to force a Conformity thereto; elſe he would not have teſtified in Print on this wiſe, <hi>They that ſet up</hi> Outward Things, <hi>gathers People to themſelves, not unto God, and that it is below Wiſdom to jangle about</hi> Outward Things. See his <hi>General Epiſtle</hi> Printed for <hi>M. W.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To return, I ſhall now ſay ſomething further touching the advice to call in the ſaid Book Entituled the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> though as I ſaid before, I dare not call it in on the Foot of that advice, given as aforeſaid, yet if the occaſion wherefore it was publiſhed, be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I ſhould therefore, ſo far as concerns me, be ready to aſſent that all things therein relating to matter of Difference and Reflection be called in, and buryed in the Grave of Oblivion; firſt taking liberty to collect and publiſh (if it ſhould be ſo with me) what is therein <hi>Doctrinally</hi> written.</p>
               <p>To give an account of all the Occaſions wherefore it was Printed; and afterwards Publiſh't amongſt Friends, is too large, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do refer the <hi>Reader</hi> to the Book it ſelf (eſpecially the <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Poſcript</hi> thereto) for Satisfaction in that, nothing doubting but that whoever ſhall peruſe it through, and not in <hi>Spirit of Prejudice,</hi> will eaſily diſcern, that ſufficient occaſion was given to Juſtifie my ſo ding, and that all the Revilings of my Adverſaies on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, may worthily return as ſo many <hi>Darts</hi> to pierce the Bowels of their <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However it is with me further to add, That if our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> are for Peace, we are ſo to, let them give but the like <hi>Demonſtration</hi> for it as we have done, and I doubt not but it will enſue, and though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101053:7"/>one Expedient frequently propoſed by us, hath been to forgive all apprehended Offences againſt each other, as aforeſaid, yet let the <hi>Reader</hi> know that we have not at any time propoſed any thing on our part, to ſhun a <hi>Juſt Tryal</hi> of any thing that hath, or may be laid to our charge for that we have called for, deſiring that Chriſts Rule might be exalted as a <hi>Standard,</hi> to Try <hi>us</hi> and our <hi>Oppoſers,</hi> viz, <hi>By their Fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi> And when we have propoſed For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of all apprehended Offences, as aforſaid, it hath been chiefly to ſhew how willing we were to forbear any further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Nakedneſs in our <hi>Oppoſers;</hi> but ſince our Adverſaries ſeem to be ſuch a ſort of People, as that nothing but <hi>Summum Jus</hi> (and that according to their own ſenſe of Juſtice (againſt thoſe with whom they are not at Unity) will ſerve their turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: what is the reaſon that ſo much Partiality hath appeared amongſt them, as that a Cry for Juſtice againſt <hi>George Fox</hi> cannot be heard, as well as againſt any other Perſon? Alas! can ſuch think us ſo beſotted, as to give heed to Exhortations for excluding Jealouſie whil'ſt the Cauſe thereof remains: If our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> are really willing that we ſhould embrace that Counſel, we propoſe as an Expedient thereto, as followeth,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let a Teſtimony from the chief of our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> be drawn up when they are Aſſembled at their <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> againſt the Impoſition of <hi>Outward Forms</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an <hi>Eſtabliſh't Church-Government,</hi> by one or more Members of Chriſts Body, to be a Bond upon other Members of the ſame Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to perform, whil'ſt otherwiſe perſwaded in their own Minds, unto which let <hi>George Fox,</hi> as well as others, ſubſcribe, with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration by <hi>George Fox,</hi> that he neither did, nor doth deſign by any thing given forth by him, any ſuch <hi>Impoſition</hi> as by theſe Lines we deſire may be declared againſt. This is now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, becauſe Juſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See Chriſtian-Quaker the</hi> 4th. <hi>Part.</hi>
                  </note> Occaſion of <hi>Jealouſy</hi> hath been given that he hath deſigned to impoſe a ſtrict Obſervance of his <hi>Outward Orders,</hi> and that under as ſevere Penalties as his, and his Adherents Power will admit and extend to.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Foraſmuch as <hi>George Fox</hi> ſtands charged with divers things reproachful to the Truth, and that <hi>Jealouſies</hi> have entred many, that no Cry or Call for Juſtice againſt him, will be hearkned unto by his Party, for fear of his ſevere Cenſures, <hi>as if what he binds in Earth, is bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd in Heaven.</hi> Let a Teſtimony as aforeſaid be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101053:8"/>drawn up, that it is but Juſt, that <hi>George Fox</hi> ſhould abide a Tryal in ſuch a Caſe; and not only ſo, but let us be informed, before whom ſuch a Tryal ought to be, and thus may our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, lay a Foundation to exclude Jealouſies that have entred.</p>
               <p>I now come to take ſome particular notice of the aforeſaid Books. The Title of that given forth under the Name of <hi>Chriſtopher Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> runs thus. <hi>An Epiſtle of Caution to Friends, to take heed of a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Spirit that is entred into</hi> William Rogers, <hi>and his</hi> Abetters, <hi>as appears in his malitious Book, falſly called the</hi> Chriſtian-Quaker, <hi>&amp;c. who under the Profeſſion of primitive Truth, are betraying it to the World, and putting Truths Lambs into their Bear-Skins for the World to worry, becauſe they have no Power to do it themſelves, who have publiſhed their wicked Book in</hi> Askelon, <hi>the Fire of their Infamy, and have told it in</hi> Gath, <hi>the Wine-preſs to preſs out their ſour Grapes, to ſet the Peoples Teeth an edge againſt the Lambs of God, with whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Advice and Counſel by way of Information, that the Simple-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded may not be inſnared by the Crafts and Wiles of Satan, through ſuch fallen Antichriſtian Inſtruments as</hi> William Rogers, <hi>and ſuch as are entred into the ſame malitious Spirit with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ingenious Reader from ſo large a Title, could expect leſs than one Citation out of what I publiſhed, being above fourſcore Sheets, to manifeſt the reaſonableneſs (at leaſt) of one recrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting part of his Title, but that he hath not done; nay, he is ſo far from it, that he doth not pretend to cite one word out of all my Book, more than the beginning of my very <hi>Title, viz.</hi> The <hi>Chriſtian Quaker</hi> diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Apoſtate and Innovator,</hi> &amp; yet his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence is ſo great, (as page the 3d.) to accuſe me, that my end in writing and printing, <hi>is to abuſe and miſrepreſent the faithful People of the Lord (and eſpecially ſuch as have been Faithful) Eſpecially that Dear and Eminent Servant of God</hi> George Fox, <hi>and to contradict his Bleſſed Life, in which</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Chriſtopher Taylor) <hi>he is ſtill made Inſtrumental in the Hand of the Lord, to bring forth Bleſſed Things for the Service of God and his Truth, from the Oracles of the Divine Breath, to the Praiſe of his Name for ever.</hi> As to <hi>Chriſtopher Taylors</hi> laſt cited word, <hi>for ever,</hi> if his meaning be with relation to <hi>George Fox,</hi> I ſay, that if he had added, <hi>if he keeps his Place and Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Truth to the end,</hi> it would have ſhewed a better Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſince we learn from the Holy Scriptures, <hi>That if a Righteous Man turn from his Righteouſneſs, and commit Iniquity, his Righteous Deeds which he hath done ſhall not be remembred.</hi> To be plain, if his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101053:8"/>meaning be as aforeſaid,
<note place="margin">Note, <hi>his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> John Blayk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>aſcribed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Honour to</hi> George Fox. <hi>See the Fifth Part of the</hi> Chriſtian-Quaker, <hi>page</hi> 77.</note> it is cauſe of Jealouſie that <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor</hi> thinks that <hi>George Fox</hi> is more than a man (as a publick Preacher, on Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe had touching <hi>George Fox,</hi> once told me) and not only ſo, but ſuch an one as ſhall never err nor fall, elſe what is the meaning that <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor</hi> ſhould, not only uſe the word <hi>for ever</hi> ſo unwarily, if he ſpoke it with relation to <hi>George Fox,</hi> but alſo reflect upon me at that ungodly rate, as he hath, and yet not mention any one particular thing diſtinct from a general Reflection, more than what he ſaith of me touching <hi>George Fox</hi> as aforeſaid; for if a meer Oppoſition to <hi>George Fox,</hi> or ſome other Man againſt whom I have written be not in it ſelf Evil (even as a meer Oppoſition to the Son of God that never erred is) there is no reaſon for any one to take notice of one word written by <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor</hi> againſt me; eſpecially ſince what I have brought forth in Print touching <hi>George Fox,</hi> was after I had written to him many Letters of my Diſſatisfaction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, and uſed my utmoſt Endeavour by writing to the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meeting,</hi> by ſpeaking and writing to many Eminent Friends in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and at length by Travel into divers Parts of the Nation on purpoſe to manifeſt the neceſſity that lay upon me to clear my Conſcience in Print, unleſs Satisfaction might be ſo far given, as that I might obtain a hearing before Friends in Truth; but that could not be obtained, and my naked end was, that if my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint ſhould appear to them to be juſt, even as it was in it ſelf, it might without reſpect of Perſons be taken notice of accordingly. For a more particular account of my Chriſtian Proceedings and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for appearing in Print, I refer to the <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> to the firſt five Parts of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis worthy Obſervation, that there is a <hi>Preface</hi> to <hi>Chriſtopher Taylors</hi> Epiſtle, ſubſcribed by <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> wherein he thus ſaith, <hi>To all ſuch who have, or may have itching Ears to read the Book</hi> (<hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> Chriſtian-Quaker) <hi>it riſes in my Heart to caution you to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, ſatisfying your Minds therein, for the Enemy may take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage upon you, thereby to draw out your Minds to take every thing for granted that is therein Inſerted, and ſo cauſe you to look out at others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of looking after trimming your own Lamps.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Conſideration of theſe Lines compared with one Part of <hi>Chriſtopher Taylors</hi> Title, <hi>viz.</hi> with wholſome Advice and Counſel
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101053:9"/>by way of Information, that the ſimple-minded may not be enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, leads me to obſerve,</p>
               <p>That the beſt way, (as to me appears) that our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> have to keep the Simple-Minded from being inſnared, is to pin their Faiths on ſuch as <hi>John Bringhurſt</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor</hi> are, and an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number of uncertain qualified Perſons, called the <hi>Second-days Meeting.</hi> 'Tis eaſy to diſcern what a <hi>Body of Darkneſs</hi> is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under ſuch ſort of Council, for if it take place, then thoſe who are Simple-minded are no longer to ſee and hear for themſelves, but in the moſt favourable Conſtruction, muſt, according to a late Doctrine, have their Eye to the Brethren: and yet me-thinks I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a confuſion amongſt our <hi>Oppoſers,</hi> even relating to this matter; for the Subſtance of this Doctrine hath been of late alſo publiſhed in publick Meetings for Worſhip, as before is hinted at, <hi>viz. As in the natural Body the Eye is placed to ſee for all the reſt of the Members, ſo alſo in the Spiritual;</hi> and hath been explained, ſo as that it hath ſometimes been taken, <hi>That</hi> George Fox <hi>is an Eye for the whole Body,</hi> and other times, <hi>As if ſome other Perſon were an Eye for a Meeting,</hi> neither of which Explanations agrees with this Doctrine, <hi>Have your Eye to the Brethren.</hi> Many Heads and Horn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be exalted with ſuch kind of Doctrines as theſe, by which the Preachers of the <hi>Light of Chriſt,</hi> as in the beginning, may become a ſcorn and diriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <q>
                     <hi>Oh Babyloniſh Building,</hi> the God of Heaven, <hi>ſaith My Soul,</hi> appear in his due time, to pull it down Root and Branch, that ſo that bright and glorious day wherein we were made Partakers of a meaſure of Chriſts Light, Spirit, and Grace, renewing the Mind unto God by the vertuous Operation thereof in our own illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Hearts (whereby we came to drink clear and pure water out of our own <hi>Ciſterns</hi>) may not at length be ſo obſcured and overſhadowed with ſuch a <hi>Vail of Darkneſs,</hi> as that any one of us may be zealouſly affected to partake of the muddy waters of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Ciſtern,</hi> and reject our own that is pure.</q> So much at preſent may ſuffice to ſay on the occaſion taken from <hi>Chriſtopher Taylors</hi> Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>I now come to take a little notice of <hi>Thomas Laurence</hi>'s Sheet, the Title runs thus, William Rogers <hi>his</hi> Chriſtian-Quaker <hi>manifeſted to be</hi> Antichriſtian, he tell the Reader, <hi>That he hath written a Book againſt</hi> Seperatiſts, <hi>That the Price thereof is a</hi> Half-penny, <hi>That he is</hi> 81 <hi>Years of Age, and that two chief Points in Writing, is to be</hi> Plain <hi>and</hi> Short, <hi>That mine is neither</hi> Plain <hi>nor</hi> Short, <hi>but</hi> Ambiguous, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101053:9"/>Doubtful, <hi>loaded with many</hi> Lerters, Suppoſitions, <hi>and</hi> Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, Reiterations, <hi>and</hi> Parentheſis, <hi>many and long</hi> Objections, <hi>that will both trouble and weary the</hi> Reader. I confeſs <hi>Thomas Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> hath avoided the <hi>Rock</hi> that I by his Account have run upon, however, as ſhort as he is, he is not free from many Miſtakes, I will not call it, <hi>his Brethrens Method of Lying,</hi> becauſe Charity ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iges me to think <hi>Thomas Laurence</hi> makes Conſcience not to tell a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and known Lye, and I am the more engaged to call them by the name of <hi>Miſtakes,</hi> becauſe of his Age, which he ſaith, is 81 Years, and that in the numbering the Sheets of my Book, he hath miſtaken many, for he ſaith they are 100 Sheets, when as they want of 90.</p>
               <p>A part of his Miſtakes in his own words, are theſe,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Thou haſt abuſed <hi>George Fox</hi> double, 1ſt. Judged him by <hi>Hear-ſay,</hi> 2dly. Judged him for adviſing to hide Goods in any Caſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> You Preach up Doctrine, but leave out Chriſts-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſo you are rightly called <hi>Seperates,</hi> putting aſunder what God hath joyned together, parting <hi>Huſband</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi> cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the <hi>Body</hi> from the <hi>Head,</hi> as if they were all Traytors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That we have aſſerted many things that are not true, but proves it not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That <hi>George Fox</hi> was the firſt that did begin the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference amongſt Friends by ſetting up <hi>Monthly</hi> and <hi>Quarterly Meetings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That the <hi>Seperates</hi> (a nick-name put upon us) will have no increaſe of <hi>Chriſts Government,</hi>and yet in the 28 p. of the <hi>Third Part</hi> of my Book, I aſſert in theſe words, <hi>And ſince 'tis undoubtedly ſo that of the Increaſe of Chriſts Government there ſhall be no End.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That we charge our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> with <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Hypocreſy,</hi> that profeſs themſelves Members of the <hi>True Church,</hi> and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves as the <hi>Church</hi> Believes.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Laurence</hi> quotes the Words of Chriſt as cited by me, <hi>viz. As I hear, I Judge,</hi> that is, ſaith <hi>Thomas Laurence, hear the Party, not report,</hi> and ſo by his own falſe Conſtruction of Chriſts words cited by me, gives himſelf trouble to no purpoſe, he further cites theſe following words, <hi>That the Lord hath anointed and choſen</hi> George Fox <hi>to be in that Place amongſt the Children of Light in this our day, as</hi> Moſes <hi>was amongſt the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in his day, to ſet up Forms of</hi> Church-Government. The Subſtance of the Words are laid down by me as ſeeming to be deducible from an <hi>Objection</hi> raiſed in the 9 pag. of the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> he alſo ſaith that in the 29th.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101053:10"/>page of the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> I aſſert <hi>That the Place of Chriſts Government is only within in the Heart:</hi> and further alſo, that I aſſert <hi>It is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Light in our Conſciences to believe that Chriſts Government ſhould reſt upon any Man or Men to be Rulers over others.</hi> He quotes not the Page, that I may examine whether theſe laſt words are ſo laid down or not.</p>
               <p>At preſent, I have no Concern to trouble the <hi>Reader</hi> with what he ſaith thereto, nor yet the reſt of his Sheet, which for the moſt part, is touching his ſenſe of <hi>Chriſts Government,</hi> and to exalt the Service of <hi>George Fox</hi> above the Service of <hi>John Wilkinſon</hi> and <hi>John Story,</hi> his own Lines compared with his <hi>Title-Page,</hi> and my <hi>Book,</hi> is, without any further Reply, ſufficient to ſhew his weakneſs, my end in citing what <hi>Thomas Laurence</hi> hath cited of my words, is chiefly to ſignifie that what I have ſo noted, is all that he hath cited out of my Book to prove it <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> which when compared with the aforeſaid Catalogue of Miſtakes, will no way erect the <hi>Title-Page,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note. <hi>A very Eminent Preacher as Tho. Laurence hath ſaid, dictated that Title unknown to him, and contrary to his Mind.</hi>
                  </note> nor yet the <hi>Perſon</hi> that was Dictator thereof, nor yet the <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> at <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſervations on the Book, partly in the Name of <hi>John Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and partly in the name of his Mother <hi>Mary Pennington.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Title-Page</hi> runs thus, John Penningtons <hi>Complaint againſt</hi> William Rogers, <hi>relating to the Abuſe and Injury done to the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his worthy Father</hi> Iſaac Pennington, <hi>in miſrepreſenting and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting ſome of his Writings in his Book Entituled the</hi> Chriſtian-Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereunto is ſubjoined ſomewhat to manifeſt his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mary Penningtons</hi> not ſhunning Sufferings for Truth, <hi>&amp;c. oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by</hi> William Rogers <hi>his ſuggeſting the contrary.</hi> From the <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-Page</hi> two things may be expected by the <hi>Reader</hi> to be proved, Firſt, <hi>That I miſrepreſent ſome of his Fathers Writings,</hi> and Secondly, <hi>That I pervert them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are both notoriouſly falſe, and ſo will appear to any unbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed Underſtanding <hi>Reader,</hi> the Proof given by <hi>John Pennington,</hi> is words of mine which he cites out of the 88 pag. of the <hi>Third Part</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> viz. <q>We think it neceſſary to cite a Teſtimony publiſhed in Print by <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi> the Younger in the Year 1660, being part of a diſcourſe, Entituled the <hi>Authority
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101053:10"/>and Government which Chriſt excluded out of his Church.</hi>
                  </q> As it lies altogether word for word, and not taken by Parts and Pieces here and there, theſe are all the Words of mine which he quotes for Proof, and having done, he treats thereon, as if my words import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that I here would cite the whole Teſtimony of the ſaid <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi> word for word, and not by Parts and Pieces here and there, when as my very words, as they are cited by the ſaid <hi>John Pennington,</hi> clearly ſhew that my Intent and Purpoſe was to quote only one part of his diſcourſe, Entituled, <hi>The Authority and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which Chriſt excluded out of his Church;</hi> as it lay altogether word for word, and not taken by parts and Pieces here and there, which I faithfully performed, beginning at the beginning of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph after a full ſtop, and ſo quoted about eight or ten ſides, without adding or deminiſhing a word, and at length left off at a full ſtop, nothing ſaid by <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi> contradicts this, the reaſon occurring in my Mind wherefore I ſo worded my meaning, could not be to inſinuate that I cited the whole Teſtimony, becauſe my very words declare that 'twas but a part, and the Motive wherefore I inſerted theſe words as it lay altogether, and not by parts and Pieces here and there, was chiefly to quit my ſelf from Jealouſie that I had acted according to the Example of one of my <hi>Oppoſers</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> who on a certain occaſion had taken out of my writing a part of a Sentence in one place, ſpoken on an occaſion ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred one day, and a part of a Sentence in another place, on an occaſion adminiſtred another day, and renders them in Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript as one entire Sentence ſpoken by me.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as <hi>John Pennington</hi> hath not laid down any of my words, to ſhew wherein I have perverted ſome of his Fathers Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I think it neceſſary to cite all that I ſay in relation to that Part of his Fathers Teſtimony which I have cited; out of which words <hi>Perverſion</hi> muſt be proved againſt me, or elſe none can be proved at all; the words do immediately follow what he hath cited to ſhew Miſrepreſentation, and are theſe, <q>Our End in citing this Teſtimony is, that the <hi>Impartial Reader</hi> may conſider whether the ſaid Teſtimony hath any Coherence with that part of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Note, <hi>meaning</hi> Rob, Barclais<hi>'s Book of Government, wherein he writ of a ſort of Perſons that would be</hi> Innovators, <hi>and given to change, and introducing</hi> New Doctrines <hi>and</hi> Practiſes, <hi>not only differing, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to what were deliver'd in the Beginning, reflectingly treating on ſuch kind of Language as this, I muſt ſtay until convinced.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Book of Government</hi> which is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101053:11"/>againſt by us, or doth contradict any Subject Matter that we have treated upon:</q> which clearly ſhew that we put no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions on his Fathers words; but left the <hi>Reader</hi> free without endeavouring to impoſe any ſenſe relating to theſe words.</p>
               <p>And yet his weakneſs (if not wickedneſs) is ſo great as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that my Deduction (which in reality was none at all) was not genuine, but forced, and that my Inferences are not true.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe that I had not worded my meaning ſo cautiouſly, as to have ſignified 'twas only a part of his Fathers Diſcourſe, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all men of Underſtanding, whether in that very caſe, all Chriſtian Profeſſors that ever appear as publick Preachers, or Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, might not by the ſame Rule be reflected on when they have quoted by way of Teſtimony or Illuſtration, a part only of anothers Teſtimony, but that which yet ſeems to aggravate <hi>John Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> abuſe of me,
<note place="margin">Note, <hi>John Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington cites not all the reſt of his Fathers Teſtimony, but a part thereof, I therefore query, whether by his Rule he hath not proved himſelf wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of worſe Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons than he gives me, ſince he informs not his</hi> Reader, <hi>that what he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to mend the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as he may think, is only a part of the reſt of his Fathers Teſtimony.</hi>
                  </note> is this, after he had cited what he thought meet of his Fathers words to manifeſt that I miſrepreſented and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted his Fathers words; he then in the 6th. page of his Book thus ſaith, <hi>Now let us ſee, whether even out of that very Part,</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Rogers <hi>hath quoted, there be not words to the ſame effect, as where</hi> Page 94, Part 3d. <hi>of</hi> William Rogers<hi>'s Book. My Father ſaith,</hi> 
                  <q>Care muſt be had, that nothing Govern in the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> but the Spirit of Chriſt, that nothing elſe teach, nothing elſe exhort, nothing elſe admoniſh and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, nothing elſe cut off, and caſt out, again, every Member is to wait in that Meaſure of the Spirit which he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to feell the going forth of the Spirit in him that teacheth and governeth, and ſo be ſubject, not to Man, but to the Lord, to receive from the Lord, to obey the Lord.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To every unprejudiced <hi>Reader,</hi> that may rightly weigh what I have now written, and compare <hi>John Penningtons</hi> Lines with the pretended occaſion thereof, I doubt not but it will be manifeſted that I have not miſrepreſented, nor perverted his Fathers Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and yet <hi>John Pennington,</hi> for no other cauſe than already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, reflects on me on this wiſe, <q>That I do not through Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101053:11"/>but wilfully, and deſignedly endeavour to ſmite and vilifie ſuch as were, and are honourable, that I am guilty of premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and palpable Falſhood, that I have traduced his Father, and ſo proceeds to charge me with down right <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and <hi>impious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varications,</hi> and with a <hi>Judas Kiſs,</hi> (meaning as he ſaith, a ſhew of <hi>Candor,</hi> &amp;c.) I labour to betray the <hi>Truth</hi> and its <hi>Sincere Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> into the Hands of the <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly,</hi> that I was untrue to my word, further adding on this occaſion, theſe very words, <hi>viz.</hi> Theſe baſe and under-hand Dealings are ſo far from becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>tender Friend,</hi> that they are not like a <hi>fair Adverſary,</hi> and ſo unſuitable to a <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> that they would be cauſe of ſhame to a <hi>Mortal-Heathen,</hi> and that I prevericate in the Face of the World, and ſo appeals to any <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbyaſed Judicious Reader,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I have not dealt fallaciouſly, deceitfully, and ſurreptitiouſly, as well as unrighteouſly, that I appear againſt the <hi>Truth,</hi> and them that are in it.</q> All which undeſerved Reflections, together with the heaps of the like in <hi>Chriſtophers Taylors</hi> Epiſtle, ſeem to ſhew that the Approvers and Subſcribers act like ſuch as have had their Educations at <hi>Billings-gate</hi> amongſt the <hi>Scolds,</hi> rather than under the Roofs of ſober Families. One thing I have yet omitted, that was with me to take notice of. <hi>John Pennington</hi> in favour, as he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, of his Father, tells his Reader, that I have leapt over ſome Leaves at the beginning, explanatory of the reſt, and left out an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Sentence at the cloſe, from whence I obſerve, that what I quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted might reaſonably be termed Explanatory of that which did proceed, and not that which proceeded be explanatory of what I quoted, which did follow. The Sentence left out at the Cloſe was this, <hi>And the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity being thus kept, all will come into one Outwardly at length, as the Light grows in every one, and as every one grows into the Light, but this muſt be patiently waited for from the Hand of God, who hath the right way of affecting it, and who alone can do it, and not harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cruelly attempted by the rough hand of man.</hi> Touching this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>John Pennington</hi> ſaith, that I knew it would not ſerve my turn, but if fairly and impartially ſet down, would have both mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Work inſignificant, and detected the falſeneſs of my Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it could not but have manifeſted to every conſiderate <hi>Reader</hi> that my Deduction was not genuine, but forced; to this I ſay, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That I made no Deduction or Inference from his Fathers words, as I have already proved. <hi>Secondly,</hi> His Fathers words are <hi>Prophetical,</hi> ſignifying what will come to paſs, not what was come to paſs, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101053:12"/>ſince the occaſion of my citing his Fathers words, was only in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a Diſcourſe touching what had been, I ſhould have ſhewn my ſelf very impertinent, to quote his words <hi>Prophetically ſpoken,</hi> of what ſhould be: However, ſince <hi>John Pennington</hi> is pleaſed to ſay, I knew it would not ſerve my turn, but would have rendred my Work inſignificant; I ſhall take the liberty to tell him that thoſe very words may juſtly be termed to be a ſufficient Teſtimony againſt ſome Actions whereof <hi>George Fox</hi> and ſome of his Party are guilty in an high degree.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Witneſs, the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution raiſed againſt</hi> P.S. <hi>and</hi> I.W. <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome mention is made in the</hi> 1ſt. <hi>and</hi> 4th Parts <hi>of my</hi> Chriſtian-Quaker, <hi>and Proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> John Ainloe <hi>at a Quarterly-Meeting in the Iſle of</hi> Ely.</note> For it is certainly known that he and ſome of his Party have harſhly, and (ſo far as was in their Power) truely perſecuted ſome Perſons for not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming to the <hi>Outward Preſcriptions</hi> of others, but had they inſtead thereof, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to wait on the Lord for a further growth in the Light, in order to the being led into an <hi>Outward <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> or <hi>Conformity</hi> to ſuch <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> by the Hand of the Lord, who alone (as <hi>John Penningtons</hi> Fathers Teſtimony is) hath the right way of effecting it, it would have more agreed with his Fathers Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the Principle of Truth.</p>
               <p>To conclude my Obſervations on <hi>John Penningtons</hi> Book, I have this to add, that <hi>John Pennington</hi> declares that the drift of the 3d. <hi>Part</hi> of my Book, as the <hi>Title-Page</hi> imports, <hi>Is to tye up all to an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Government of Chriſt, excluſive of any Outward Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Order, or Deſcipline.</hi> This it ſo notoriouſly falſe, that my very expreſs words in divers places of that very part doth contradict it; 3d. <hi>P. pag.</hi> 24. I thus write, <hi>Though the Principle of Truth in theſe latter days hath, and may further lead into the Practiſe of Outward Orders in Diſcipline, with Relation to the Church of Chriſt.</hi> And pag. 25. thus, <hi>For though ſome Outward Form or Appearance may be according to the Order of the Goſpel.</hi> And in pag. 19. thus, <hi>And yet I am abundantly ſatisfied that Set and Appointed Meetingt on certain prefixt days, being with the joynt concurrence of thoſe Members aſſembling, and from time to time to be aſſembled, to take care of the Poor, to inſpect Marriages, that none come together diſorderly, and to take care that Truth may not be ſcandalized through the Backſlidings of ſuch who have been in Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Children of Light, are not inconſiſtent with that Form that the Powor of God may lead into; for I am a Witneſs for many years paſt, even to this day, that ſuch Meetings have been ſerviceable to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thoſe righteous Ends.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="observations">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101053:12"/>
               <head>My Obſervations on what is written in relation to <hi>Mary Pennington.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Title-Page Imports, <hi>That I have ſuggeſted, that</hi> Mary Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington <hi>did ſhun Suffering for Truth.</hi> 'Tis a very falſe Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what I have ſaid concerning her: For there cannot be a ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Suffering for Truth, unleſs one ſhun that Suffering which Truth requires, which I never did charge <hi>Mary Pennington with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However I think meet to ſignifie the Occaſion of my uſing her Name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi> ſends a Paper of Queries to be read in divers Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, reflecting ſo far as Queries could, on ſuch as ſecured any part of their Eſtates from the <hi>Spoiler,</hi> and being informed that he adviſed <hi>Mary Pennington</hi> to ſecure hers from the Spoiler, I ſent unto him this Query, Whether thou <hi>George Fox,</hi> whil'ſt <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi> was in Priſon, and in expectation of being premunired, did not adviſe, or at leaſt encourage <hi>Mary,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Iſaac Pennington,</hi> to ſecure her, or their Eſtate, if thou deny it, I ſhall undertake to prove it, or bring Teſtimony under the hand of a credible Friend in Truth that <hi>Mary Pennington</hi> did ſignifie ſo much? this I did to manifeſt at leaſt <hi>George Fox</hi> his changeableneſs in his Anſwer to the ſaid Query: He denies not the Matter, and <hi>Mary Pennington</hi> relates ſomething of it more at large, Saying, <hi>That ſhe never had any Advice from</hi> George Fox <hi>contrary to her own Conſcience,</hi> and at laſt ſaith thus, <hi>And now I have given the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e relation, I ſum up all that, what I have here aſſerted to be done by me, was no ſhift nor carnal hiding from Spoil in that.</hi> That was a Teſtimony, which being compared with that part of her Relation, where 'tis ſignified, <hi>That when Sufferings for Meetings by Impriſonment gave way to proceedings by Fines upon Preachers, Hearers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Lord gave me a clear quiet ſubmitting to it, though I had in my view the Ruine and Havock that</hi> 40 l.<hi>a week would procure to us,</hi> &amp;c. Shews that a Suffering for Meetings is in her ſenſe a Suffering for a Teſtimony, and that ſhe was not free to avoid that, but a Suffering for not Swearing, ſhe was free to avoid, which occaſions me to add that Purſuant to the Apoſtles Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, we cannot forſake the Aſſembling of our ſelves together, and in purſuance of Chriſts Command, we cannot Swear, and in both
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101053:13"/>theſe our Teſtimonies for <hi>Truth</hi> is concerned; and therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but conclude, that as it related to avoiding Sufferings, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Obedience to Chriſts Command, <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Counſel to her was not Juſtifiable in him, whil'ſt be condemned the Practiſe in another, as it related to Sufferings in purſuance either of his or the Apoſtles Counſel; and whereas <hi>Mary Pennington</hi> hath accuſed me, that I have aſperſed innocent Servants of the Lord, and have brought forth nothing to prove that I have ſo done, I return it as a falſe Charge, unbecoming the Pen of one that pretends to an innocent and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Converſation, as ſhe doth.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>BRISTOL, the</hi> 
                     <date>9th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1681.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>William Rogers</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:101053:13"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
